[Rigsby]
SO WE GOT KIRBY HINES,
29-YEAR-OLD LOCAL BOY,
WELDER.
THAT'S PRETTY MUCH
ALL WE GOT.
LOCAL P.D. HAS STOMPED
ALL OVER THE CRIME SCENE,
SO I DON'T THINK FORENSICS
WILL BE ANY USE.[Lisbon] IT'S LIKE THEY
DON'T EVEN WATCH TV.
EVERY TODDLER
KNOWS THIS STUFF.HEY, LISBON. HOW YOU DOING?
HEY, PAT. LONG TIME.
WHAT'S THE DEAL?UH, T.O.D. LOOKS TO BE
YESTERDAY AFTERNOON,
GIVE OR TAKE.
YOUR STANDARD BLUNT-FORCE TRAUMA
TO THE BACK OF THE HEAD--
MAYBE ONE STRIKE FOLLOWED BY
A COUPLE OF REAL WIDOW MAKERS.
LENGTH OF WOOD, I'M GUESSING.WHAT'S THAT ON HIS FACE?
IS THAT GLITTER?
[chuckles] YEP.
RIDING THAT DISCO FARM BOY TIP.
[horn honks]
HIS FAMILY'S HERE.
GONNA GET UGLY, I EXPECT.[man] GO ON. KEEP GOING ON.
I'LL SEE YOU LATER.
RIGS, VAN PELT,
WORK THE BODY. CHO.
[indistinct shouting]
HEY.[man shouting indistinctly]
AND I KNOW YOU
DAMN WELL KILLED HIM!
INTERESTING.
[lowers voice] I FEEL LIKE
JANE KNOWS ABOUT US.[lowers voice] NO, HE DOESN'T.
HOW WOULD HE KNOW?
I KNOW WE'VE BEEN COOL.
IT'S JUST IT FEELS
LIKE HE KNOWS.YOU'RE BEING PARANOID.
JUST BECAUSE
I'M BEING PARANOID
DOESN'T MEAN
THAT JANE DOESN'T KNOW.
[man] DON'T TELL ME
YOU DIDN'T KILL HIM, TED.THAT POOR BOY LYING THERE--
HE'S JUST FOOL ENOUGH
TO MARRY YOUR DAUGHTER.YOU'RE GOIN' DOWN.
YOU'RE DEAD.
BRING IT RIGHT AHEAD, DOOLEY!
HERE I STAND.YOU'RE DEAD!
THAT'S ENOUGH.
THAT'S ENOUGH.YOU STEP OUT OF MY ROAD,
GIRLIE. HERE I AM, DOOLEY!
BACK OFF, MAN!
WE'RE GRIEVING, YOU CLOWN!
WHY DON'T YOU BACK UP?!YEAH? YOU MAKE ME, PISSANT.
[crowd gasps]AAH!
[screams]
NICELY DONE.YOU'RE UNDER ARREST.
LET'S GO.
[grunting]
ALL RIGHT, ALL RIGHT.
OKAY.
[crying]
SIR,
LET ME GET THIS STRAIGHT.
THE VICTIM'S WIFE
IS DONNA HINES,
AND IT WAS
HER BROTHER ROD GERBER
THAT TOLD YOU TO STEP BACK.
IS THAT RIGHT?
MY NAME IS THEODORE LUSCOM.
I AM A CITIZEN
OF FREE CALIFORNIA.
THE SO-CALLED FEDERAL AND STATE
AUTHORITIES YOU WORK FOR
ARE NOT LEGITIMATE.
THEREFORE, I DO NOT
RECOGNIZE YOUR RIGHT
TO ARREST OR QUESTION ME.
OH, PLEASE.YOU DON'T KNOW IT,
BUT YOU PEOPLE ARE JUST TOOLS
OF THE UNITED NATIONS.
OH, YEAH, WE KNOW IT.
THEY TOLD US LAST JUNE,
LAID IT ALL OUT.SAY WHAT?
THERE WAS A CHANGE OF POLICY.
HAD A BIG SECRETIVE MEETING,
TOLD US EXACTLY
WHO WE'RE WORKING FOR.
THAT, MY FRIEND, WAS
AN EYE-OPENER, I TELL YOU. WOW.ARE YOU MOCKING ME?
OH, I'M SERIOUS. THEY TOLD US...
[whispers] THE WHOLE GRAND PLAN.
HUSH.
IGNORE HIM, MR. LUSCOM.
GOOD STUFF.
[engine starts]
JUST IGNORE ME.
LISBON?HEY, BOSCO. WHAT'S UP?
YOU'RE NOT GONNA LIKE
WHAT I'M ABOUT TO DO,
BUT YOU'RE GONNA HAVE
TO DEAL WITH IT.[Lisbon] WHAT?
HEY, BOSCO.HI, JANE. YOU'RE UNDER ARREST.
HMM?
♪♪
IT'S A MICROPHONE TRANSMITTER
LOCATED DURING AN ELECTRONIC
SWEEP OF OUR OFFICES.
THAT IS A DEDICATED RECEIVER
TO THE UNIT
WHICH I FOUND IN JANE'S DESK.IS THIS TRUE, JANE? YOU WERE
SPYING ON BOSCO AND HIS TEAM?
"SPYING" IS
SUCH AN UGLY WORD.
MORE JUST KEEPING
A FRIENDLY EYE ON THINGS.
DID YOU KNOW ABOUT THIS?OF COURSE NOT. I WOULD HAVE
NEVER ALLOWED THIS.
SHE WOULD NEVER.
YOU UNDERSTAND THIS IS
A SERIOUS CRIMINAL OFFENSE?
COME ON.
EAVESDROPPING IS A FELONY
UNDER SECTION 632
OF THE PENAL CODE,
PUNISHABLE BY UP TO ONE YEAR
IN PRISON.HOW COULD YOU BE SO STUPID?
HE HAS THE RED JOHN CASE.
HE WON'T KEEP ME INFORMED.
SO I HAVE TO
KEEP MYSELF INFORMED.
I WAS LOW-KEY ABOUT IT. I COULD
HAVE TURNED ONE OF HIS AGENTS
OR USED BLACKMAIL OR BRIBERY.
I DIDN'T.
WELL, THANKS FOR YOUR RESTRAINT.
WE CAN RESOLVE THIS EASILY.
IT'S YOUR CHOICE.
HOW'S THAT?
IF JANE RESIGNS IMMEDIATELY
AND AGREES TO NEVER RETURN
TO THE CBI,
I WILL ASK THE A.G.
NOT TO FILE CHARGES.
BOSS.
YOU KNOW BOSCO HAS THE RIGHT
OF IT. NOTHING I CAN DO.
NOTHING I WANT TO DO, FRANKLY.
HE CROSSED A LINE.
WHAT'S IT GONNA BE, JANE?
CHARGE ME.
I'LL SEE YOU IN COURT.
I'M NOT GONNA LEAVE THE CBI
JUST 'CAUSE YOU TELL ME TO.
IF I CHARGE YOU,
YOU'LL GO TO JAIL NOW--TODAY--
AND YOU CAN'T APPLY
FOR BAIL TILL TUESDAY.
SO THAT'S THREE DAYS
AND NIGHTS IN JAIL.IT'S A NEW EXPERIENCE.
I WELCOME IT.
DON'T BE STUPID.
THIS IS SERIOUS.
COME ON, SAM.
YOU REALLY WANT TO DO THIS?
I JUST DID. MALLOY!
HE'S READY TO GO.
[bell rings]
OPEN TWO.
[buzzer sounds]
[man] HEY, GUYS.
[door closes]HEY, PETE.
DID YOU SEE ANY VERMIN
OUT IN THE CORRIDOR THERE?VERMIN?
MICE.
NUH-UNH.
SEE? TOLD YOU.
YOU'RE PARANOID, MAN.
I KNOW WHAT I SAW.
THE ARRESTING OFFICER ADVISES
PROTECTIVE CUSTODY.
ARE YOU A COP
OR A CHILD RAPIST?
NEITHER.
WHAT DO YOU NEED
PROTECTIVE CUSTODY FOR, THEN?
WELL, I GUESS I DON'T.
YOUR FUNERAL.
[bell rings]
[indistinct conversations]
STOP.
OPEN UP NUMBER EIGHT.
[metal door clanks]
[man speaking indistinctly]
[clank]
UH...
HI. NICE TO MEET YOU.
WHAT YOU IN FOR?
OH, ME? UH, EAVESDROPPING
ON A STATE AGENT.
HMM.YOU?
THEY SAY I RAPED AND MURDERED
A GUY, STABBED HIM TO DEATH.
OH.
BUT IT'S NOT TRUE.OH, THAT'S GOOD.
WE HAD CONSENSUAL SEX.
THENI STABBED HIM TO DEATH.
OKAY.
YOU GET THE TOP BUNK.
I LIKE THE TOP BUNK.
[mutters]
I KNOW. I-I KNOW.
IT'S SAD AND IT'S STUPID,
BUT JANE WAS BOUND TO
SELF-DESTRUCT EVENTUALLY.
WE ALL KNEW THAT.BUT, BOSS, COME ON.
THERE MUST BE SOMETHING--
LET'S GET BACK TO THE CASE,
SHALL WE?
IS THAT THE BOOK WE FOUND
ON THE VICTIM?YEAH, KIRBY WOULDN'T WIN
ANY PENMANSHIP AWARDS.
IT'S MOSTLY ILLEGIBLE.LOTS OF NUMBERS. TIMES, MAYBE?
MAP COORDINATES.
BIBLE CITATIONS.
THERE'S A FEW NAMES
I CAN MAKE OUT--JAY, MARTIN.
AND THEN ON THIS PAGE...
"VULTURES!!!"?
SOMEBODY'S PREYING ON HIM,
WAITING FOR HIM TO DIE?
PREYING ON HIM FOR WHAT, THOUGH?
HE WASN'T A RICH MAN.
CHO, GET TO WORK ON TED LUSCOM.
VAN PELT AND I ARE GONNA GO
TALK TO KIRBY'S FAMILY
IN THE MORNING.
RIGSBY, GET ON THE HINESES.[Rigsby] OKAY, YOU GOT IT.
SO, TED,
TELL US ABOUT YOUR BEEF
WITH KIRBY HINES
AND THE GERBERS.
I GET TO CALL YOU
BY YOUR FIRST NAME, TOO?
IF YOU LIKE. I'M KIMBALL.
[chuckles] AIN'T YOU SMOOTH
AND EASYGOING?
[exhales]
THAT 10 ACRES
WHERE KIRBY DIED--
THAT WAS
MY GRANDFATHER'S LAND.
20 YEARS BACK, MY FATHER'S
BROTHER ROY STOLE IT
FROM US RIGHTFUL PROGENY
AND FRAUDULENTLY SOLD IT
TO THE GERBERS, WHO KNEW.
THE GERBERS
KNEW HE STOLE IT.
AND HOW MUCH IS 10 ACRES
OF LAND WORTH AROUND THERE?
OH, HELL, MAN.
IT AIN'T THE LAND.
IT'S WHAT'S UNDER IT--
OIL SANDS.
IT USED TO BE WORTHLESS.
COST TOO MUCH TO PUMP OUT.
BUT WITH THE PRICE
OF OIL SKY-HIGH,
OIL SANDS ARE WORTH WORKIN'.
WE'RE TALKING $50 MILLION,
$60 MILLION TO THE LANDOWNERS.
SO YOU TOOK THE GERBERS
TO COURT.
YEAH...
LAST YEAR.
AND WHAT
DO YOU THINK HAPPENED?
YOU GOT NOTHING.
ZERO.
I KNEW I SHOULDN'T
HAVE WASTED MY TIME,
BUT THE DECEIT AND DISHONESTY
HAS MADE ME MAD.
WHERE WERE YOU YESTERDAY,
TED?
WELL, I WAS SEVERAL PLACES,
KIMBALL.
WE'RE GONNA NEED A LIST.
"WE"? I ONLY SEE ONE OF YOU.
I AND THE STATE MACHINERY
OPPRESSION'S
GONNA NEED A LIST.
WELL, I WILL THINK IT OVER.
SOME PEOPLE JUST DON'T
HAVE THAT FACILITY.
I'M SURE YOUR FATHER
LOVED YOU IN HIS WAY.
HE JUST DIDN'T HAVE THE TOOLS
TO EXPRESS THAT LOVE.
[voice breaking]
YOU KNOW WHAT, MAN?
I REALLY APPRECIATE YOU
LISTENING TO ME, MAN.
PLEASE, BOO.
WHAT ARE CELLMATES FOR?
[exhales]
SO LISTEN.
LISTENING.
ABOUT THE, UH,
UNFORTUNATE SITUATION
WITH JANE,
I WANT YOU TO KNOW
THAT MY BEEF
IS ONLY WITH HIM.
I GOT NO PROBLEM
WITH YOU OR YOUR PEOPLE.
IT WAS A BIG MISTAKE BRINGING IN
A WHACK JOB LIKE HIM,
BUT THAT'S IN THE PAST NOW.
YOU AND ME...
YOU AND ME ALWAYS HAD
A GOOD WORKING RELATIONSHIP,
AND I HOPE THAT CAN CONTINUE.
OKAY.
I LISTENED.
SO WE'RE COOL?
YOU DID WHAT YOU THOUGHT
WAS RIGHT.
I NEED TO THINK ABOUT IT BEFORE
I KNOW WHETHER WE'RE COOL.
OKAY.
OKAY, FAIR ENOUGH.
[Patrick yawns]
GOOD NIGHT, JANE.
GOOD NIGHT, PAL.
AND DON'T WORRY
ABOUT TOMORROW MORNING.
WHY WOULD I NEED TO WORRY
ABOUT TOMORROW MORNING?
THERE ARE SOME
SCARY PEOPLE HERE.
THEY ALL KNOW YOU'RE A COP.
HOW WOULD THEY KNOW THAT?
I'M NOT--I'M NOT REALLY A COP.
WELL, THEN YOU'LL BE FINE.
BESIDES, THEY GOT REAL EXCELLENT
MEDICAL FACILITIES HERE.
[sighs]
GRACE?
SORRY.
IS SOMETHING WRONG?
NO. I WAS--I WAS THINKING ABOUT
JANE. I HOPE HE'S ALL RIGHT.
HE'LL BE FINE.
MAYBE HE'LL LEARN SOMETHING.
HI. ARE YOU GAIL?
YES.
IS YOUR MOM HERE?
ARE YOU FROM THE POLICE?
YES, WE ARE.
CAN YOU TAKE US TO YOUR MOM?
ARE YOU GONNA
BRING MY DADDY HOME?
NO, SWEETIE, I'M SORRY.
WE CAN'T DO THAT.
[shouting indistinctly]
[man] WHAT?
[indistinct conversations stop]
SHH.
GOOD MORNING, EVERYBODY.
MORNING, PIG.
[laughter]
THANK YOU FOR RAISING
THAT ISSUE.
LET ME ADDRESS THAT.
YOU BELIEVE ME TO BE A POLICEMAN
OF SOME KIND. THAT IS NOT TRUE.
I AM NOT A POLICEMAN,
NOR HAVE I EVER BEEN ONE.
I DO WORK WITH THE POLICE. I USE
MY SKILLS TO CATCH MURDERERS,
THOUGH RARELY DO I DEAL
WITH PROFESSIONALS
SUCH AS YOURSELVES.
WHAT SKILLS?
MM. PEOPLE SKILLS.
YOU SHOW ME YOUR SKILLS,
LITTLE BROTHER. [sniffs]
YOU...
ARE THE SHOT-CALLER IN HERE.
YOU COME FROM THE BAY AREA.
YOU LIKE TO SNIFF SOME KIND
OF GLUE OR SOLVENT TO GET HIGH.
YOU WISH YOU COULD QUIT,
BECAUSE YOU THINK IT MAKES YOU
LOOK WEAK
IN FRONT OF YOUR PEERS.IS THAT RIGHT? [sniffs]
YES, BUT YOU NEEDN'T WORRY,
BECAUSE THE WAY YOU ARE
WHEN YOU GET HIGH
MAKES EVERYBODY
EVEN MORE SCARED OF YOU, RIGHT?
[man] HELL YEAH, MAN.
YEAH.[men laughing,
speaking indistinctly]
[man] FOR SURE.
I DON'T THINK
I LIKE YOU MUCH.
IF YOU STOP SEEING THE WORLD
IN TERMS OF WHAT YOU LIKE
AND WHAT YOU DISLIKE
AND SAW THINGS
FOR WHAT THEY TRULY ARE
IN THEMSELVES,
YOU WOULD FIND A GREAT DEAL
MORE PEACE IN YOUR LIFE.
AND I CAN HELP YOU
WITH THAT IF YOU WANT.I, UH--
THINK ABOUT IT.
WHERE'S THE PHONE IN HERE?
I NEED TO MAKE A CALL.OVER THERE.
THANKS.
[men mutter and laugh][Lisbon] THIS IS NICE.
THANK YOU.
MM.DID YOU MAKE THESE?
WE BOTH DID.MMM.
WE'RE KEEPING OURSELVES BUSY.DELICIOUS.
YOUR SHOW'S IN THE VCR, BABY,
IF YOU WANT TO WATCH IT A WHILE.
OKAY.
WE'RE SORRY FOR YOUR LOSS,
DONNA.
IT'S HARD.[pouring liquid]
IT'S HARD.
JUST WHEN THINGS
WERE GETTING BETTER.
THINGS WERE GOING BADLY?
UM, YOU KNOW,
MARRIAGE STUFF.
ME AND KIRBY HAVE BEEN TOGETHER
SINCE JUNIOR HIGH.
PEOPLE CHANGE
WHEN THEY GROW UP.HOW SO?
UM, WE KIND OF DRIFTED,
I GUESS.
MY FAMILY, THE GERBERS--
WE'RE VERY CLOSE.
IT CAN BE TOO MUCH WHAT WITH US
LIVING HERE TOGETHER AND ALL.
KIRBY GOT TO FEELING KIND OF
SQUASHED UP AGAINST 'EM.
HE WAS A LONE WOLF TYPE.
LIKED TO BE IN THE WOODS
ON HIS OWN, YOU KNOW?
WAS THERE ANYONE IN PARTICULAR
HE HAD A PROBLEM WITH
OR WHO HAD A PROBLEM WITH HIM?
NO.
NO, JUST ME.
AND LIKE I SAY, WE'D BEEN
DOING BETTER RECENTLY.
HE WAS BEING
MORE HONEST WITH ME,
OPENING UP
ABOUT HIS FEELINGS.
YOU KNOW HOW MEN CAN BE.
YES, WE DO.
MONEY PROBLEMS?
NO, MA'AM.
KIRBY WAS A SKILLED WELDER.
[voice breaking] ALWAYS A GOOD
PROVIDER AND PROUD OF IT.
AND THEN YOU HAVE
THE OIL MONEY COMING IN.
YES, MA'AM.
HOW MUCH DO YOU STAND
TO GAIN?
UM, THEY SAY EACH
OF US YOUNGER COUSINS
WILL GET AROUND
$80,000 A YEAR.
I HAVE TO POINT THIS OUT
TO YOU, DONNA.
THAT GIVES YOU
STRONG MOTIVE HERE.
KIRBY WAS ENTITLED
TO HALF YOUR MONEY.
IF YOUR MARRIAGE
WAS IN TROUBLE,
THAT WOULD MAKE YOU PRETTY
UNHAPPY, WOULDN'T IT?
OUR MARRIAGE
WASN'T IN TROUBLE.
THE CORONER TELLS US THERE
WERE MANY UNHEALED BRUISES
AND CONTUSIONS ON HIS BODY,
WHICH SUGGESTS AROUND
THREE WEEKS BEFORE HIS DEATH,
KIRBY WAS PRETTY BADLY
BEATEN UP.
I DON'T--I DON'T KNOW
ANYTHING ABOUT THAT.
[Patrick] NEXT TIME YOU FEEL
THE URGE TO GET HIGH,
MAYBE YOU'LL SEE
YOUR MOTHER'S SMILING FACE.
MAYBE YOU'LL ALREADY FEEL
WARM, SAFE AND HAPPY.
MAYBE YOU'LL REALIZE THAT HIGH
FEELING YOU GET FROM DRUGS
IS AN ILLUSION,
NOTHING MORE THAN CHEMICALS
MOVING AROUND IN YOUR BRAIN.
[woman] INMATE JANE. INMATE
JANE TO THE VISITING ROOM.
INMATE JANE
TO THE VISITING ROOM.
[sniffs]MORE LATER.
YOU ARE DOING GREAT.
[buzzer sounds]
THAT'S THE CASE PAPERWORK
SO FAR.
THAT'S A COPY
OF THE VICTIM'S NOTEBOOK.MM.
AND THOSE ARE
SOME SUDOKU PUZZLES.
STILL LIKE LUSCOM FOR IT?
YEAH, HE'S GOT
ATTITUDE AND MOTIVE.
BUT THE CORONER SAYS
KIRBY HINES WAS BADLY BEATEN UP
ABOUT A MONTH AGO, AT WHICH TIME
LUSCOM WAS IN CUSTODY
ON A D.U.I.
AND RESISTING ARREST BEEF.COULD HAVE BEEN ONE OF
LUSCOM'S FRIENDS THAT DID IT.
YEAH, ONLY HINES
NEVER REPORTED A BEATING,
DIDN'T GO TO A HOSPITAL, AND HIS
WIFE DENIES ANY KNOWLEDGE OF IT.
[raps table]YOU THINK KIRBY AND HIS WIFE
COULD HAVE KEPT QUIET
ABOUT THE BEATING
'CAUSE IT WAS A FAMILY MATTER?YEAH. LISBON'S WITH
THE FATHER-IN-LAW NOW.
KIRBY TOOK A BEATIN' LAST MONTH?
I DON'T RECALL THAT.
FROM THE WAY DONNA REACTED
WHEN I ASKED HER ABOUT IT,
IT SEEMED TO BE
A FAMILY MATTER.
MAYBE YOU OR YOUR SON RODDY
GOT INVOLVED
IN DONNA'S MARITAL PROBLEMS?[chuckles] NO.
NO, MA'AM, THAT'S WAY OFF.
WELL, HEY, BABY CAKES.HI.
YOU OKAY?
ARE YOU SICK OR SOMETHING?DO I LOOK SICK?
WELL, IT'S NOT LIKE YOU
WALKING AROUND IN SWEATS,
NO MAKEUP, YOUR HAIR
ALL UP LIKE THAT.WELL, EXCUSE ME.
MY STEPDAUGHTER'S
HUSBAND JUST DIED.
I'M GRIEVING.THAT'S COOL. THAT'S COOL.
WHO'S YOUR FRIEND?OH, THIS IS AGENT LISBON
FROM CBI, COME ABOUT POOR KIRBY.
MY WIFE SANDRINE.
HMM. I NEED TO GO
TO THE MALL.
WHAT'S YOUR THEORY,
SANDRINE?
WHO KILLED KIRBY?
WELL, I DON'T KNOW.
DO I HAVE TO HAVE AN ANSWER?
I THOUGHT THAT WAS
YOU GUYS' JOB.WORTH ASKING.
I'LL BE HONEST.
I'M SORRY KIRBY'S DEAD,
BUT I'M NOT SORRY
MY DAUGHTER ISN'T MARRIED
TO A LOSER ANYMORE.IN WHAT WAY WAS HE A LOSER?
HE WAS A BUZZKILL.
THE GERBER FAMILY'S MOVING ON
UP, AND KIRBY DIDN'T LIKE THAT.
HE LIKED BEING POOR
AND WHATEVER.
NO VISION. DONNA DESERVES
MORE THAN THAT. RIGHT, SAND?
MM-HMM. SHE'S A TREASURE.
[chuckles]
AGENT BOSCO, A WORD?
SURE.
I KNOW YOU'RE BUSY,
SO I WON'T TAKE UP YOUR TIME
SHOOTING THE BREEZE, BEATING
AROUND THE BUSH AND ALL.THAT'S WHAT YOU'RE DOING.
[Cho] WE WANT TO TALK
ABOUT JANE.LOOK, WE KNOW THAT JANE
CROSSED THE LINE,
BUT YOU HELP US OUT HERE
AND, UH,
WE'LL BE EXTREMELY GRATEFUL.
WE'LL OWE YOU BIG-TIME.
[drops papers]OH, OKAY. I SEE.
SO LET'S SAY I, UH, REACH OUT
FOR YOU TO DO SOME STUFF.
WHAT KIND OF STUFF?
WELL, THE KIND OF STUFF THAT
NEEDS TO GET DONE SOMETIMES,
YOU KNOW,
TO TAKE THE BAD GUYS DOWN,
KEEP THE GOOD GUYS
WALKING AROUND.
NOTHING ILLEGAL. MAYBE A LITTLE
RULE BENDING ON THE DOWN LOW.
THAT'S NO PROBLEM.
SEE, THAT'S MY EXACT POINT.
THERE IS A PROBLEM.
THERE'S NO RULE BENDING
IN THE CBI.
YOU TWO GUYS ARE GOOD AGENTS,
BUT JANE HAS CORRUPTED YOU.NO, HE HASN'T.
SO YOU WERE READY TO BEND
THE RULES BEFORE HE GOT HERE?
THANKS FOR YOUR TIME.NICE TALKING TO YOU.
"VULTURES!!!" "VULTURES!!!"
WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
[sniffs]WHO ARE JAY AND MARTIN?
YOU KNOW, VULTURES PEE ON
THEIR LEGS TO COOL THEMSELVES.
[sniffs]HMM. IS THAT RIGHT?
[sniffs]
YES, OF COURSE.
WHAT DOES "VULTURES!!!" MEAN?VULTURES ARE BIRDS.
NO KIDDING.
Hines was a bird-watcher.
THAT'S WHY HE HAD BINOCULARS.
HE SAW JAYS AND MARTINS
AND VULTURES.
GOT IT. GOOD.
SO THAT'S A DEAD-END.NO, ON THE CONTRARY,
IT'S A BREAKTHROUGH.
I NEED TO SPEAK
WITH RODDY GERBER.
I GOTTA ASK HIM
SOME QUESTIONS.WELL, RIGSBY'S
GONE TO MEET HIM.
TELL ME, AND I'LL TELL RIGSBY
WHAT TO ASK HIM.OH, NOW WHERE IS THE FUN
IN THAT FOR ME?
Can't you bring Gerber
in here?NO.
OKAY, NO PROBLEM.
I'LL SORT IT OUT.
I'll call you back.WAIT. YOU...
[cell phone chirps]HEY, JAILY.
UH, LISTEN, I JUST WANT
TO GIVE YOU THE HEADS-UP.
I HAVE A VERY STRONG FEELING
RODDY GERBER IS GONNA BE
HOSTILE AND AGGRESSIVE
TOWARDS YOU,
SO YOU SHOULD PROBABLY BE
VERY CAREFUL WITH HIM.
DON'T WORRY. I THINK
I CAN HANDLE RODDY GERBER.
Well, I'm just warning you.
APPARENTLY,
HE'S A VERY TOUGH GUY.YEAH, WELL, I'D LIKE
TO SEE HIM TRY SOMETHING.
WE'LL SEE HOW TOUGH HE IS.
WHATEVER.
Roddy Gerber?
YEAH, WHO WANTS TO KNOW?
AGENT RIGSBY, CBI.
I'M ON MY WAY TO YOUR LOCATION.
I have a couple of questions
I'd like to ask you first...
discreetly.YEAH?
I'VE HEARD FROM A COUPLE
OF RELIABLE SOURCES
THAT YOU AND KIRBY HINES
WERE HAVING AN AFFAIR,
uh, some kind of
sexual relationship.
THAT'S A DAMN LIE.Are you sure, Roddy?
LYING TO A CBI AGENT IS
A VERY SERIOUS OFFENSE.
I WAS IN THE MARINE CORPS.
OH, REALLY? WELL,
THAT SAYS IT ALL. I'M EX-ARMY.
MARINE CORPS SUCK EGGS.
But, hey, no point in arguing
over the phone.
WE'LL SORT THIS OUT WHEN
I GET OUT TO YOUR LOCATION.
SEMPER FI, SISSY BRITCHES.
[engine turns off]
RODDY GERBER?
AGENT RIGSBY, CBI.
[buzzer sounds]
RODDY.
HEY, THANK YOU SO MUCH
FOR COMING.
[chuckles]
[dominoes click]
SO, RODDY,
TELL ME ABOUT THE VULTURES.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT.
SURE YOU DO.
I DON'T LIKE YOUR TONE.
MAN, WE TALKING
OR WE PLAYING? COME ON.
KIRBY FOUND TURKEY VULTURES
NESTING ON YOUR LAND, DIDN'T HE?
NO, HE DIDN'T.
TURKEY VULTURES ARE DYING OUT
BECAUSE OF A LOSS OF HABITAT.
THEY'RE A PROTECTED SPECIES.
IS THAT RIGHT?
YEAH, IT IS.SERIOUSLY NOW, YOU'RE
DISRESPECTING THE GAME.
[click]
THANK YOU.ONE MOMENT. THEY'RE PROTECTED,
WHICH MEANS IF THEY'RE
NESTING ON YOUR LAND,
YOU CAN'T DRILL FOR THE OIL,
AND YOU DON'T GET RICH.
[click]THAT RIGHT?
YES, IT IS.
SO WHEN KIRBY
TELLS YOU ABOUT THE NEST,
YOU TELL KIRBY TO SHOW YOU
WHERE THE NEST IS
SO THAT YOU CAN DESTROY IT.NO.
ONLY KIRBY DOESN'T WANT TO TELL
YOU, SO YOU BEAT HIM UP A LITTLE
UNTIL HE DOES TELL YOU.
THEN YOU GO AND YOU SHOOT
THE VULTURES,
AND YOU DESTROY THE NEST.NO.
BAD LUCK TO KILL LARGE BIRDS
UNLESS YOU EAT 'EM.
YOU DIDN'T EAT 'EM, DID YOU?HELL NO!
HA! BUT YOU ADMIT
YOU SHOT 'EM, THOUGH.THEY'RE VULTURES, MAN!
YOU THINK I'M GONNA GIVE UP
A MILLION BUCKS
OVER A COUPLE UGLY MOTHERS
WHO EAT DEAD PEOPLE?
NO FRICKIN' WAY.
SO YOU SHOT 'EM.
YEAH, I DID.
ANYBODY WOULD.
I CAN'T DISAGREE.
AND KIRBY?
NO, NOT ME.
I KICKED HIS ASS, YEAH.
I DIDN'T KILL HIM.
NO NEED. WHAT THE HELL'S
HE GONNA DO TO ME?
YOU SWEAR ON YOUR MOTHER'S GRAVE
YOU DIDN'T KILL KIRBY?
I SWEAR ON MY MOM'S GRAVE
I DIDN'T KILL KIRBY.
INTERESTING.
NO, NO, NO. I THINK YOU SHOULD
TAKE LEAD. IT'S A FEMALE THING.
NO, IT'S NOT. SHE'S FEMALE,
THAT'S ALL. HE'S NOT.
YOU SHOULD TAKE LEAD.WHY ME?
YOU'RE ALWAYS BEING,
YOU KNOW, TOO DIRECT.
SHE WON'T BE OFFENDED.WHO WON'T BE OFFENDED?
NOTHING. WELL...
UH, WE WERE THINKING...
THINKING'S GOOD.
ABOUT?WE WENT TO BOSCO AND ASKED HIM
TO GIVE JANE A BREAK,
BUT HE WOULDN'T.
SO WE WERE THINKING MAYBE
IF YOU WENT AND ASKED BOSCO
TO LET JANE GO
AS A PERSONAL FAVOR TO YOU,
BETWEEN FRIENDS, HE'D DO IT.WHY WOULD YOU SAY THAT?
WELL, YOU KNOW...IT'S OBVIOUS.
HE HAS A THING FOR YOU--
SEXUAL THING.WE'RE NOT SAYING YOU HAD
AN AFFAIR OR ANYTHING,
IT'S JUST THAT--HE LIKES YOU A LOT, IT SEEMS--
THE WAY HE LOOKS
AT YOU SOMETIMES.
YOU'RE MISTAKEN. BOSCO HAS
NO PARTICULAR LIKING FOR ME,
AND EVEN IF HE DID, I WOULDN'T
USE IT AS LEVERAGE FOR JANE.
WHY NOT?BECAUSE THE LAW IS THE LAW.
JANE BROKE THE LAW, AND NOW HE'S
GOT TO PAY THE CONSEQUENCES.
[cell phone rings]
OH, HI, JANE.
[sadly]
I NEED YOU TO COME VISIT ME.
WHY? WE'RE BUSY.
PLEASE, LISBON?
IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT.
I NEED TO SEE YOU.
ALSO A BLUEBERRY MUFFIN.
[grunts]
LOOKS LIKE CRANBERRY.
THEY DIDN'T HAVE ANY BLUEBERRY.
WHAT'S UP?
[lowers voice]
RODDY GERBER'S INNOCENT.
THAT'S IT?
PRETTY MUCH. WELL, NO.
RODDY BEAT UP KIRBY
SO HE'D TELL HIM
WHERE THE, UH, PROTECTED
VULTURES WERE NESTING
SO RODDY COULD KILL THEM, BUT HE
SAYS HE DIDN'T KILL KIRBY,
AND I BELIEVE HIM.
HE SWORE ON HIS MOTHER'S GRAVE.
THAT'S INTERESTING,
BUT YOU COULD HAVE
TOLD ME THAT ON THE PHONE.
I NEEDED A VISITOR SO I COULD
GET INTO THE VISITORS ROOM.
HOW I WISH I HAD MY GUN.
HEY, CRIME-FIGHTING'S HARD.
SUCK IT UP.
[whispering] LOOK,
THAT'S WHY WE'RE HERE.
DOOLEY GERBER?I NEED TO ASK HIM A QUESTION.
WHAT QUESTION?ANY QUESTION.
IT DOESN'T MATTER.
CAN YOU KEEP THE GUARD OFF ME?
COULD YOU, PLEASE?
HEY.
[normal voice] IT'S OKAY.
[normal voice]
DOOLEY, YOU CAN TELL ME.
THE TRUTH IS YOU KILLED YOUR
SON-IN-LAW. ISN'T THAT TRUE?
AND WHO ARE YOU NOW?
THAT'S A VERY GOOD ANSWER.
THANK YOU.
SO?
WHAT'D YOU LEARN?
WELL, THAT WAS
JUST A CONTROL QUESTION.
THE NEXT QUESTION I ASK HIM
IS THE CRITICAL ONE.YOU KNOW WHAT?
I DON'T NEED MY GUN.
I CAN JUST HIT YOU
WITH MY CHAIR.
I THINK YOU'LL FIND IT'S BOLTED
TO THE FLOOR. [chuckles]
DO YOU UNDERSTAND
WHAT'S HAPPENING TO YOU?
YOU COULD GET
A PRISON SENTENCE.
I UNDERSTAND THAT
YOU'RE KEEPING ME IN JAIL
IN THE HOPES THAT YOU
WILL TEACH ME A LESSON.
IT'S NOT GONNA WORK.
I AM NOT KEEPING YOU IN JAIL.
THE LAW IS KEEPING YOU IN JAIL.
THE LAW,
AS PLAYED BY SAM BOSCO,
AND YOU CAN MAKE SAM BOSCO DO
ANYTHING WHENEVER YOU LIKE.
RIGHT. BECAUSE HE'S
SO IN LOVE WITH ME,
I CAN MAKE HIM DO WHATEVER.
YES.
NO. NO, I WAS ONLY SAYING THAT
BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT RIGSBY
AND THE GUYS
WERE JUST SAYING.
IT'S TOTAL NONSENSE. SAM BOSCO
IS A HAPPILY MARRIED MAN.
HE HASN'T THE FAINTEST
INTEREST IN ME THAT WAY.
I HAVE NO INFLUENCE
OVER HIM WHATSOEVER.
THE GUYS NOTICED IT, TOO?
I'M IMPRESSED.
HE'S VERY RECESSIVE
IN HIS PASSIONS.
HARD TO SPOT THAT
HE'D KILL AND DIE FOR YOU.
TRUST ME,
YOU ARE WAY OFF.
INTERESTING PUZZLE
YOU PRESENT.
LIES AND TRUTH
ALL MIXED TOGETHER.
LOOK, I HOPE WE CAN GET YOU
OUT OF THIS MESS.
BUT IT'S ALSO TRUE
THAT I DO HOPE THAT
YOU LEARN A LESSON
FROM THIS.
THERE ARE REAL BOUNDARIES
IN LIFE.
THESE ARE REAL PRISON WALLS.
[whispers] ONLY IN YOUR MIND,
LISBON. ONLY IN YOUR MIND.
[man] Officer exiting six.
[buzzer sounds]
[door closes]
[chittering]
[squeaking]
[squeaks]
[bell ringing]
[man] REC CENTER
BREAKFAST CALL.
HEY, HELP! HEY, HELP!
HEY, DEPUTY!
HEY, HEY, MAN,
WE GOT A MAN DOWN, MAN!
HE AIN'T MOVING! DEPUTY, I GOT
A MAN DOWN! WE NEED HELP, MAN!
OH, CRAP. WE HAVE
AN INMATE DOWN, LEVEL NINE.
NUMBER EIGHT OUT LIKE A LIGHT.
DID YOU DO THIS?NO, MAN,
I DIDN'T TOUCH HIM, MAN!
HE JUST AIN'T MOVIN', MAN!
'SUP WITH HIM?
DAMNED IF I KNOW. HE WAS
LIKE THIS WHEN I GOT THERE.
OKAY, LEAVE HIM HERE.
I'LL CALL THE MEDIC.
YOU GUYS GO GET BACK ON POST.
GOT A CUSTOMER FOR YOU.
NO.
OKAY.
[man speaks indistinctly]
[muttering indistinctly]
WHAT ARE YOU SAYING?
[whispers] MY HAND.
HAND?
[squeals]
[voice breaking]
STEVE, COME QUICK.
WE GOT A PROBLEM, STEVE.
I NEED HELP.
I NEED HELP![buzzer blaring]
HEY! HEY! NO, NO, NO![mouse squealing]
HEY! SOMEONE! SOMEONE![banging on door]
PRISONER LOOSE!
THERE'S A PRISONER LOOSE!
HELP!
HELP, SOMEONE!
[buzzer continuing,
guard shouting indistinctly]
MORNING.
[man] HEY! HEY!
HELP! SOMEBODY!
HEY!
LISBON,
I HAD A HORRIBLE DREAM.
I DREAMT THAT JANE
ESCAPED THE COUNTY JAIL.
I DREAMT THAT THE SHERIFF,
THE A.G. AND THE DISTRICT SUPER
ALL CALLED TO YELL AT ME.
NOW YOU'RE GONNA
WAKE ME UP, YES?
I'M SORRY, SIR.
I HAVE NO EXCUSE FOR HIM.
HE IS BEYOND OUT OF LINE.
HE'S BLOWN IT, ALL RIGHT.
WE HAVE AN A.P.B. OUT,
BUT MAYBE YOU CAN CONTACT HIM,
PERSUADE HIM TO COME IN QUIETLY.
NOBODY WANTS HIM TO GET HURT.CONTACT HIM HOW?
PERSUADE HIM HOW?
YOU TWO ARE CLOSE.
HE'LL LISTEN TO YOU.
THAT'S VERY FUNNY.WHAT IS IT FUNNY?
IT JUST IS.[cell phone rings]
[Patrick] Hi, Sam.
WHERE ARE YOU?
Dooley Gerber's house.
IF YOU SEND THE SHERIFF OVER,
I'LL HAVE KIRBY'S KILLER
IN TEN MINUTES OR SO.JANE, YOU DAMN FOOL!
THANK YOU.
WHAT THE HELL
ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT?
YOU SAID YOU HAD
KIRBY'S KILLER.
NOT YET, BUT I LIKE
TO BE AN OPTIMIST.
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE THE MAKINGS
OF A CUP OF TEA, WOULD YOU?
THANK YOU.
YOU'RE WELCOME.
MMM.
SO LISTEN, UH, RODDY TOLD ME
ABOUT THE VULTURES
AND WHAT HE DID TO KIRBY. HOW
DID YOU COPE WITH THAT, DONNA--
YOUR HUSBAND BEING
BEATEN BY YOUR BROTHER?
HOW DID YOU FEEL ABOUT THAT?
ANGRY.
WITH WHO?
MYSELF, MY FAMILY.
KIRBY WAS A GOOD MAN,
AND I LET HIM DOWN.OH, HON.
NO. NO, DADDY, IT'S TRUE.
I LET THE MONEY BLIND ME.
WE ALL DID.
EXCUSE ME.
I GOT STUFF TO DO.OH, PLEASE DON'T GO,
SANDRINE.
I WAS JUST GONNA SAY
HOW FUNNY IT IS WHEN YOU HAVE
A BIG FAMILY FIGHT,
IT CAN CLARIFY A SITUATION.
DO YOU THINK
THAT HAPPENED AT ALL?I WISH.
MAYBE KIRBY FOUND CLARITY.
MAYBE KIRBY REALIZED
HOW, UH, IMPORTANT IT WAS
FOR HIM TO BE TRUTHFUL.
WHEN WE FOUND POOR KIRBY,
HE HAD SOME FLECKS
OF GLITTER ON HIS FACE.
AND WHEN I SAW YOU, DOOLEY,
AT THE PRISON,
YOU HAD SOME GLITTER
ON YOUR FACE, TOO,
WHICH MEANS YOU AND KIRBY
WERE IN CLOSE CONTACT
TO THE SAME WOMAN--A WOMAN
WHO LIKES TO WEAR GLITTER.
THAT WOULD BE YOU, SANDRINE.
YOU'RE STUPID.
OFTEN.
BUT I NOW ALSO SEE THAT
NEITHER DOOLEY NOR DONNA
HAD ANY NOTION OF THIS
CONNECTION BETWEEN YOU AND HE,
WHICH MEANS KIRBY
WAS VERY CONSIDERATE...
WHAT?CONSIDERATE ENOUGH TO WARN YOU
BEFORE HE CAME CLEAN
ABOUT YOUR AFFAIR.
[chuckles] OH, BABY, I SWEAR
ON MY LIFE THERE WAS NO AFFAIR.
SURE THERE WAS. YOU WERE
BORED AND FRUSTRATED.
HE WAS AVAILABLE.NO, NO, NO.
KIRBY SOON FOUND OUT
WHAT KIND OF WOMAN YOU ARE,
AND HE BROKE IT OFF, YES?
HE WANTED TO GET OUT
OF SUTTER VALLEY. HE WANTED TO
START A NEW LIFE WITH HIS WIFE,
THE WOMAN THAT
HE ACTUALLY DID LOVE.
BUT FIRST HE FELT COMPELLED
TO HAVE TO TELL
EVERYBODY THE TRUTH, THE FOOL.
HE WAS GONNA RUIN YOUR LIFE
OVER WHAT--SOME BIRDS?
FOR A BEATING THAT
HE POSSIBLY DESERVED?
WHY WOULD HE DO THAT?
YOU BEGGED HIM NOT TO TELL.
YOU BEGGED HIM,
AND HE JUST WOULDN'T LISTEN.
THIS IS ALL A LIE.
THAT NEVER HAPPENED.
YEAH, YOU HAD TO KILL HIM
RIGHT THERE AND THEN.NO! NO! IT'S A LIE.
IT'S A LIE.
I'M SORRY, SANDRINE, BUT WE HAVE
CONCLUSIVE FORENSIC EVIDENCE
FROM OUR BOYS AT THE CRIME LAB.
THE GLITTER ON KIRBY'S FACE
COVERED IN YOUR D.N.A.--COVERED.
AND D.N.A. DOESN'T LIE.
[voice trembling] I DON'T KNOW
WHERE THAT CAME FROM,
'CAUSE IT WASN'T ME.
POLICE ARE ON THEIR WAY,
SANDRINE.
I WOULD BE HONEST
WITH YOUR FAMILY,
'CAUSE YOU MAY NOT SEE THEM
FOR A WHILE.[siren wailing]
SANDRINE.
SANDRINE. SANDRINE!
OH, PLEASE!TELL ME THAT IT ISN'T TRUE.
JUST TELL ME.
HE MADE ME DO IT.[gasps]
HE MADE YOU DO IT, HUH?NO, HE--HE MADE ME DO IT!
[Patrick] SHE'LL--
SHE'LL HAVE HER PUNISHMENT.NOT ENOUGH!
AAH! OHH.
[siren bleeps]
[voice amplified] PATRICK JANE,
WE KNOW YOU'RE IN THERE.
COME OUT WITH YOUR HANDS UP.
UH, YES, IT'S ME
THEY'RE AFTER, NOT YOU.
AND THERE IS
NO D.N.A. EVIDENCE EITHER.
THAT SCIENTIFIC, FORENSIC STUFF,
IT'S--IT'S ALL VERY OVERRATED.
THANK YOU FOR THE TEA.BUT WE--
NO TAKE-BACKS.BUT YOU JUST--
AH, AH. WHOOP.
I'M COMING!
OW.
BYE.
[police radio chatter]
THANK YOU.
WHOOPS.
SO...
JANE GOT A CONFESSION
FROM SANDRINE GERBER.
CASE CLOSED.
YEAH, THE A.G.
LIKELY WON'T MAKE IT STICK,
WHAT WITH HIS KEY WITNESS
BEING IN JAIL HIMSELF--
IN FOR A GOOD, LONG SPELL ONCE
YOU ADD IN THE ESCAPE CHARGES.
THAT'S WHAT I WANTED
TO TALK TO YOU ABOUT.
I THOUGHT THIS WOULD
TEACH JANE A LESSON.
I THOUGHT HE'D BACK DOWN
OR APOLOGIZE, BUT HE DIDN'T,
AND NOW IT'S GONE TOO FAR.
YOU GOTTA LET HIM GO.
IF YOU DROP THE CHARGES,
THE A.G. WON'T CHASE IT.
WHAT IF I DON'T WANT
TO DO THAT?
DON'T MAKE ME GO THERE,
SAM.
WHAT ARE YOU SAYING,
EXACTLY?
YOU KNOW WHAT I'M SAYING.
I'LL TALK ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED
EIGHT YEARS AGO.
YOU'D GO THERE?
REALLY?
I DON'T BELIEVE YOU.
BELIEVE ME. HERE I AM.
YOU WOULD RUIN OUR LIVES,
OURCAREERS,
OVER JANE?
DOES HE MEAN
THAT MUCH TO YOU?
HE CLOSES CASES.
"HE CLOSES CASES."
IS THAT ALL IT IS?
I'M TELLING YOU IF YOU DON'T
LET JANE GO, I'LL TALK.
THAT'S ALL.
WHAT ARE YOU GONNA DO?
YEAH, OKAY, YOU DID GOOD.
BUT THERE'S TWO THINGS
PUZZLING ME.YEAH?
HOW DID YOU GET
OUT OF JAIL,
AND HOW DID YOU GET
A CHANGE OF CLOTHES?
AH, WELL, I'M GLAD
YOU ASKED THAT QUESTION.
IT WAS VERY... HEY, LISBON.HEY.
SIMPLE.SO THEY LET YOU OUT, THEN?
YES, UH, THEY DID.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.NOTHING TO DO WITH ME.
SO MODEST.
AH, RIGHT.
BOSCO'S SO IN LOVE WITH ME,
HE'LL DO WHATEVER I SAY.
YES. YEAH,
IT'S A LITTLE FAR-FETCHED.
HE DOES LOVE YOU.
HOW COULD HE NOT?
BUT HE'S NOT THE TYPE TO BEND
HIS PRINCIPLES OVER LOVE.
SO I FIGURE
IT'S SOMETHING MORE CONCRETE.
YOU MUST HAVE
SOMETHING ON HIM.YOU THINK?
YES, SOMETHING HE DID WRONG,
SOMETHING VERY BAD
THAT YOU KNOW ABOUT.
NOW HE'S NOT THE TYPE
TO STEAL OR DO DRUGS,
SO MY GUESS--HE HURT SOMEONE.
HE KILLED 'EM.
HE KILLED A BAD GUY THAT HE
COULDN'T CATCH ANY OTHER WAY.
NO.
YES, AND YOU
HELPED HIM DO IT.
NO--YOU FOUND OUT
AFTER THE FACT,
AND YOU...
LET HIM OFF THE HOOK
BECAUSE THE BAD GUY
DESERVED IT.
NO.
I'M TOUCHED THAT YOU WOULD
RISK YOUR CAREER OVER ME.
THAT MEANS A LOT TO ME.
IF YOU'RE RIGHT,
AND I'M NOT SAYING YOU ARE,
IT WOULD MEAN I BROKE
THE TRUST OF SOMEBODY
I RESPECT AND ADMIRE
FOR YOUR SAKE.
IF IT IS TRUE,
I WOULD HOPE IN THE FUTURE
YOU'D BE A LITTLE BIT MORE
MATURE AND RESPONSIBLE
IN YOUR BEHAVIOR.
I'M GRATEFUL AND ALL THAT,
BUT LET'S NOT GO CRAZY HERE.
I SHOULD HAVE
LET YOU ROT IN JAIL.
STAY TUNED FOR SCENES
FROM OUR NEXT EPISODE.